Guide to the Alexander Berkman Papers TAM.067
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Alexander Berkman Papers
1917-1919
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Berkman, Alexander, 1870-1936
Turkel, Pauline
Lohf, Kenneth A.
Issawi, Charles
TAM.067
0.5 Linear Feet (1 box)
Alexander Berkman was an anarchist and author, and companion of anarchist Emma Goldman. The collection contains legal documents, speeches and transcripts, most pertaining to Berkman and Goldman's trial for opposing conscription during World War I.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Donated by Pauline Turkel through Professor Charles Issawi and Kenneth A. Lohf of Columbia University, 1975. The accession number associated with this gift is 1975.002.
Conditions Governing Access
Materials are open without restrictions.
Historical/Biographical Note
Alexander Berkman (1870-1936) was an anarchist and author, and companion of anarchist Emma Goldman. Born in Russia to wealthy Jewish parents, he migrated to the U.S. in the aftermath of the Haymarket Riot of 1886. He spent fourteen years in prison for his attempted assassination, in 1892, of Henry Clay Frick, edited and published his own newspaper Blast, was convicted along with Goldman in 1917 of violating the Draft Act, served two years in prison, was deported, wrote several books, and in ill health, committed suicide in 1936.
Sources:
For more information, see Biographical Dictionary of the American Left, pp. 24-27.
Scope and Content Note
The papers contain primarily court transcripts and other legal documents, most prepared by Harry Weinberger, chief attorney for Berkman and Emma Goldman, reflecting Berkman's involvement with No Conscription League, his battle against extradition to California in connection with the Mooney-Billings bombing case, his and Emma Goldman's trial for violating the Draft Act by advising resistance, and their unsuccessful attempts to prevent deportation. Includes transcripts of several speeches by Berkman, a speech (1917) by Leonard D. Abbot opposing conscription, and a speech (1919) by Emma Goldman in honor of Kate Richards O'Hare; and undated portions of manuscripts of Berkman's "What is Communist Anarchism" (1929) and "Prison Memoirs of an Anarchist" (1912).
Arrangement
The folders are arranged alphabetically.
The files are grouped into 1 series:
Missing Title
Container list
Anarchism -- United States.; Communism -- United States.; Transcripts.; Speeches.; Legal documents.; Draft resisters |z United States.; No-Conscription Fellowship; O'Hare, Kate Richards, 1877-1948; Mooney, Thomas J., 1882-1942; Goldman, Emma, 1869-1940; Billings, Warren K., 1893-1972; Abbot, Leonard Dalton, 1878-1953; Weinberger, Harry, 1888-; Turkel, Pauline; Lohf, Kenneth A.; Issawi, Charles
- Papers
  - Anonymous Letter to William G. McAdoo, Secretary of the Treasury (vs. Liberty Bonds; probably not by AB), May 31, 1917 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - As We Approach the Coming Municipal Elections..., ca.1917 (Box 1, Folder 1A)
  - Case of Margaret and Jeannette Roy, Scotch Descent, Brought from Seattle to Ellis Island, Jul 12, 1919 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Deportation Hearings (Berkman & Goldman): Stenographer's Minutes, Dec 8, 1919 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Kate Richards O'Hare Testimonial Dinner, NYC: Address of Emma Goldman, Nov 17, 1919 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - London, Meyer: Letter to [photocopy], Jan 1, 1913, undated (Box 1, Folder 4A)
  - Miscellaneous, 1917-1919 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Mooney Case: Transcripts of Testimony, Speech by W. Bourke Cockran, 1917-1919 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - No Conscription League, 1917, undated (Box 1, Folder 7, Box Shared Tamiment 043)
  - Prison Memoirs of an Anarchist: Chapters 17-28 (pp. 144-291). Typescript, undated (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Prison Memoirs of an Anarchist: Chapters 29-47 (pp. 292-456). Typescript, undated (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Rough Draft of an Article to Be Released by E.B., undated (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Schwartz, Jacob: Memorial Meeting - Transcript, Oct 26, 1918 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Speech (by AB) at No Conscription League Meeting, Hunts Point Palace, NYC, Jun 14, 1917 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Telegrams Sent During Trial, 1917 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - U.S. v Goldman & Berkman: Address of Prosecuting Attorney to Jury; Charge; Sentence, Jul 9, 1917 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - U.S. v Goldman & Berkman: Berkman's Closing Speech, [1917] (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - U.S. v Goldman & Berkman: Memorandum, Petitions, Other Legal Documents, 1917 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - U.S. v Goldman & Berkman: Morning Session Transcript, Jul 2, 1917 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - U.S. v Goldman & Berkman: Morning Session Transcript, Jul 3, 1917 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - U.S. v Goldman & Berkman: Morning Session Transcript, Jul 5, 1917 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - U.S. v Goldman & Berkman: Morning Session Transcript, Jul 9, 1917 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - U.S. v Goldman & Berkman: Part of Jury Examination, Jun 27, 1917 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - What is Communist Anarchism? Chapters 1-13? (pp. 1-84), undated (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - What is Communist Anarchism? Chapters 14-20 (pp. 85-124), undated (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - What is Communist Anarchism? Chapters 14-20 (pp. 125-161), undated (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - What is Communist Anarchism? Chapters 14-20 (pp. 182-), undated (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Fragile Originals: Box 1, Folder 1, May 31, 1917 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Fragile Originals: Box 1, Folder 1A, ca. 1917 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Fragile Originals: Box 1, Folder 2, Jul 12, 1919 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Fragile Originals: Box 1, Folder 6, May 9, 1918 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Fragile Originals: Box 1, Folder 8, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Fragile Originals: Box 1, Folder 9, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Fragile Originals: Box 1, Folder 12, Jul 14, 1917 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Fragile Originals: Box 1, Folder 13, 1917 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Fragile Originals: Box 1, Folder 14, Jul 9, 1917 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Fragile Originals: Box 1, Folder 15, 1917 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Fragile Originals: Box 1, Folder 17, Jul 2, 1917 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Fragile Originals: Box 1, Folder 18, Jul 3, 1917 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Fragile Originals: Box 1, Folder 19, Jul 5, 1917 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Fragile Originals: Box 1, Folder 20, Jul 9, 1917 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Fragile Originals: Box 1, Folder 21, Jun 27, 1917 (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Fragile Originals: Box 1, Folder 22, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 16)